<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>DataSQRL Blog</title>
        <link>https://datasqrl.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>DataSQRL Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SQRL: Updating SQL for Developers]]></title>
            <link>https://datasqrl.github.io/blog/sql-for-developers</link>
            <guid>https://datasqrl.github.io/blog/sql-for-developers</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[To make it easier for developers to build data services, we developed the SQRL language which gives SQL a facelift and adds some important features to make it developer friendly, productive, and fun. Here is why we need a modern, developer-focused version of SQL.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To make it easier for developers to build data services, we developed the SQRL language which gives SQL a facelift and adds some important features to make it developer friendly, productive, and fun. Here is why we need a modern, developer-focused version of SQL.</p><p>SQL is the most popular query language and great for manipulating structured data. But SQL is not a great development language, and it's a bit ... well, old. It's a fantastic accomplishment for a 50+ year old language to be in wide-spread use today, but to keep up with the times a lot of features were bolted onto SQL that make it feel a bit frankensteinish today. Yes, we are looking at you SQL:2016.</p><p>Plus, most developers have a love-hate relationship with SQL because they primarily use it through ORMs or other abstraction layers. That level of indirection can make things unintuitive and embedding SQL as a string is just ugly. That's why ORMs have been called "the Vietnam of software engineering", and while an analogy with a major war seems a wee bit dramatic, it does capture developer feelings pretty accurately.</p><p>We believe that SQL is the best starting point if you are trying to build with data, but there are a few things missing to make it a productive choice for implementing data services.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="data-streams">Data Streams<a href="#data-streams" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Data Streams" title="Direct link to Data Streams">​</a></h2><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="relationships">Relationships<a href="#relationships" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Relationships" title="Direct link to Relationships">​</a></h2><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nested-data">Nested Data<a href="#nested-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nested Data" title="Direct link to Nested Data">​</a></h2><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="modularity">Modularity<a href="#modularity" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Modularity" title="Direct link to Modularity">​</a></h2><p>SQRL addresses these shortcomings in SQL while being fully compatible with SQL. Learn more about SQRL or follow a short tutorial to see how you can build a data service in minutes with SQRL.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>SQL</category>
            <category>SQRL</category>
            <category>database</category>
            <category>developer</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hello, World!]]></title>
            <link>https://datasqrl.github.io/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>https://datasqrl.github.io/blog/welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[We are excited to launch DataSQRL with the mission to help developers and organizations build with data.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to launch <a href="/about">DataSQRL</a> with the mission to help developers and organizations build with data.</p><p>Collectively, we have spent decades building or helping others build data services. We have seen many struggles, failures, and piles of money being thrown out the window and figured that there must be a better way. We started DataSQRL to find it.</p><p>We believe that the technologies used to build data services are too complex and that the engineering processes used to build them are broken. Here is how we plan to fix these issues.</p><p>We developed <a href="/">DataSQRL</a> which  compiles an enhanced version of SQL - called SQRL - into a fully integrated and optimized data pipeline and API server. It takes care of all the laborious plumbing, data massaging, and stitching together of technologies that makes building data services so harrowing. Check out this short tutorial to see how it works - it only takes a few minutes to build an end-to-end data service.</p><p>In addition, we are refining a value-focused process for implementing data services that we have developed over the years while working with development teams and organizations. The basic idea is to apply the same software engineering principles that have proven to be successful to implementing data services. That means you don't need a dedicated team of specialists to implement data services and can keep your customers and stakeholders in the feedback loop. Click here to learn more about our process.</p><p>That's a good starting point for enabling developers to build successful data services quickly and efficiently. But we don't think we have all the answers.<br>
We hope that you will join the <a href="/community">DataSQRL community</a> to share your experience, insights, and opinions. <br>
If you are trying to enable your organization to turn data into valuable data services, consider <a href="/services">working with us</a> and <a href="/contact">get in touch</a>.</p><p>We are excited to be on this journey and hope you will join us. Let's build with data together.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>DataSQRL</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>